Guide to the Peter Hellyer papers AD.MC.068
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Peter Hellyer papers
1973-2022
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
Hellyer, Peter
AD.MC.068
7.4 Linear Feet in 10 file boxes and 3 flat boxes, including 21 videocassettes.
Reports, correspondence, publications, news clippings, and audiovisual materials, chiefly related to the activities of British-born journalist, writer, archaeologist, and environmentalist Peter Hellyer in Abu Dhabi and the United Arab Emirates from the 1980s onward. Included are materials from the Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey, the Emirates Natural History Group, and other similar organizations in which Hellyer played a leading role in developing policies and programs related to the environment, wildlife, and cultural heritage of the United Arab Emirates. Also includes material related to Hellyer's tenure as managing editor of the daily newspaper, The Emirates News.
Conditions governing access
The collection is open for use in the Reading Room of the Archives and Special Collections department of the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Immediate source of acquisition
Acquired from Peter Hellyer in multiple accretions, 2020-2023.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into eight series: I. Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey, II. Archaeology and Cultural Heritage, III. Natural History and Wildlife Conservation, IV. Newspapers and Media, V. Publications andn printed material, and VI. Research and subject files, VII. Correspondence, and VIII. Videocassettees. Materials are usually arranged in each series alphabetic order by folder title, or sometimes within the series in chronological order. The system of arrangement was created by the processing archivist, to correspond with areas of activity in Hellyer's life as represented in these records.
Biographical note
Peter A. Hellyer (1947-2023) was born in London, England on 9 November 1947, and subsequently adopted by Arthur and Grace (Bolt) Hellyer. His parents, a horticultural journalist and teacher, raised him and his two siblings in rural Sussex. After education at Oundle School, Northamptonshire, he attended the University of Sussex, graduating with a bachelor's degree in International Relations from that university's School of African and Asian Studies in 1968. For much of the next decade, he worked as a journalist, broadcaster, and documentary filmmaker, initially based in London. He was also politically active, campaigning for Liberal party candidates in the United Kingdom, as well as participating in the movements against apartheid in Southern Africa and in support of the rights of Palestinians.
During that period, he made his first trip to the Middle East in 1969, and his first visit to Abu Dhabi in 1975, when he accepted an assignment from the joint-venture film company, UPITN (owned by the British television network ITN and the United Press International press agency), to film the official foreign visits of the founding ruler of the United Arab Emirates (UAE), Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan. His first project was to work on a documentary film about the state visit of Sheikh Zayed to France in July 1975. Hellyer later accompanied the ruler on trips to Iran, Egypt, Yemen, and Sri Lanka, among other countries, and also filmed footage of the rapidly growing city of Abu Dhabi. Following that, he was asked by the UAE Ministry of Information and Culture to direct the foreign language services of the government-run Abu Dhabi Radio, as well as the newly-developed FM radio service, Capitol Radio. In 1979 he also helped launch the English-language service of the Emirates Press Agency, also known by its Arabic initialism of WAM, working closely alongside the Agency's founding director, Ibrahim al-Abed. He remained in this position until 1982, when he returned to London, where he continued to work frequently with government officials and other individuals from the UAE. During this period, he also took part in an official visit to the UAE by a delegation from the Liberal Party, which included a meeting with Sheikh Zayed.
In 1985, the Ministry of Information and Culture offered Hellyer the position of managing editor of the first English-language daily newspaper in the UAE, the Emirates News, and he returned to Abu Dhabi to assume that position in February of that year, remaining in that role for the duration of that newspaper's existence, until January 1999.
During the 1980s, Hellyer's interests in natural history and archaeology led him to become increasingly active in groups such as the Emirates Natural History Group, in which he served as chairman from 1989-1992, and the Emirates Bird Records Committee, which sought to document all bird species observed in the UAE. In 1992 he was called to serve as Executive Director of the Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey, or ADIAS, established by Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan and under the patronage of his son, Sheikh Mohammed bin Zayed al Nahyan (who in 2022 became the ruler of the UAE). With the rapid development of many locations throughout the emirate of Abu Dhabi, whether through expansion of the transportation infrastructure or the development of sites for the drilling of petroleum, it became apparent that more work needed to be done to identify and survey potential archaeological sites before they were permanently lost. Hellyer supervised and coordinated dozens of such surveys, work that continued after the cessation of ADIAS in 2006 as well, and extending to other emirates, in particular Fujairah and Umm al Qawain. Between 2009 and 2012, Hellyer served as Project Director of the excavation of a pre-Islamic Christian monastery at Sir Bani Yas island, which had initially been discovered as part of an ADIAS survey in 1995, for the Tourist Development and Investment Company of Abu Dhabi.
From 1999 to 2004 Hellyer served as Advisor for Media, Environment and Heritage for the Ministry of Information and Culture, and following that he assumed the role of Advisor for External Communications for the National Media Council. Following the closing of the Council in 2021, he transferred to the Ministry of Culture and Youth, where he continued to work as an Advisor.
He authored or edited numerous books on the social, cultural, and natural history of the United Arab Emirates, and from 2008 until 2022 was a regular columnist for the Abu Dhabi-based English-language daily newspaper, The National. Maintaining a second home on the island of Jersey, in the Channel Islands, Hellyer was recognized for his work in building relations between the U.A.E. and the island of Jersey, and was awarded the Silver Seal by the Bailiwick of Jersey in 2012.
In 2010, Hellyer was given citizenship in the UAE by the then-President, Sheikh Khalifa bin Zayed al Nahyan, in recognition for his contributions to the state. He was also awarded the Abu Dhabi Medal in 2013.
Peter Hellyer died in Abu Dhabi on 2 July 2023.
Sources:
https://www.gatewaytouae.com/peter-hellyer [accessed June 2022]
Daniel, Kavitha. "Future Perfect." Gulf News, Nov. 22, 2002 [accessed online in July 2022]
Related materials
Material about Hellyer's activities with the observation and recording of bird species in the UAE can also be found in the Emirates Bird Records Committee records, MC.057, at the NYU Abu Dhabi Library.
Content Description
The Peter Hellyer papers are grouped into series related to his activities, while based in Abu Dhabi, in the fields of archaeology, environmental advocacy, natural history, and the media.
The first series, titled "Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey", or ADIAS, records Hellyer's role as director of that organization between 1992 and 2006, including such functions as organizing site surveys, coordinating visits of archaeologists to the emirate of Abu Dhabi in order to work on specific surveys and excavations, and reporting to Mohammed al-Bowardi, who acted on behalf of the patron of ADIAS, Sheikh Mohammed bin Zayed al Nahyan. The series of memoranda that Hellyer sent to Bowardi are especially informative about the range of activities and projects that Hellyer supervised under the aegis of ADIAS, but also contain references to projects that were part of the activities of ERWDA, or the Environmental Research and Wildlife Development Agency of the UAE, which Bowardi also oversaw. In addition to the memoranda for Bowardi, this series also contains many of the reports that resulted from archaeological site surveys conducted by ADIAS staff or contractors, in particular those in which ADIAS served as a consultant for various companies prior to construction or development on such sites. In addition to the reports, several files define the nature and scope of such consultancy work.
In addition to his role at ADIAS, Hellyer also had an active interest in archaeology represented by the second series, "Archaeology and Cultural Heritage," which contains reprints of scholarly articles presented to Hellyer by their authors, publications, archaeological surveys conducted outside of the functions of ADIAS, efforts to receive special recognition for specific sites from UNESCO, and the drafting of governmental policy related to archaeology and cultural heritage in the United Arab Emirates. The topics and dates of some of the archaeology reports overlap with Hellyer's activities in ADIAS, but were included in this series since they had no indications that they were conducted by Hellyer or others as part of their official roles within ADIAS.
The series "Natural History and Wildlife Conservation" documents Hellyer's longtime interests in the fields of ornithology, the environment, natural history, and wildlife conservation. The series consists chiefly of reports or publications from organizations such as the National Avian Research Centre, the Emirates Natural History Group, the Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia, and ERWDA. A few reports were authored or co-authored by Hellyer, while others were collected by him. Of note in this series are files related to the Al Ain Zoological Park, the mismanagement of which was highlighted in editorials written by Hellyer and published in the Emirates News, leading to a thorough investigation of that institution in 1998.
The series "Newspapers and media" reflects some of Hellyer's activities as editor of the Emirates News and as an advisor to the Ministry of Culture and Information in matters pertaining to the media. Of note in this series are files of clippings related to the trial of the Filipina domestic worker Sarah Balabagan, for the alleged murder of her employer in 1994, and the coverage of her trial in the international media. A small selection of news cuttings from Hellyer's editorials in the Emirates News are also included in this series. Also included are full sections of newspapers from Abu Dhabi commemorating National Day, the annual commemoration of the formation of the United Arab Emirates in 1971, as well special editions of newspapers following the death of the country's founding ruler, Sheikh Zayed bin Sultan al Nahyan in 2004.
The "Publications" series contains printed material collected by Hellyer, and not classified in the other series. Chief among these are publications of the Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations (ADCO), including a substantial run of that company's annual reports, from 1978-1997. In addition, this series also contains material about books authored by Hellyer.
A small selection of letters to and from Hellyer are grouped in the "Correspondence" series, includings letters from the British Liberal Member of Parliament David Steel.
The "Videocassette" series consists of VHS cassettes related chiefly to the natural and cultural history of Abu Dhabi. Both professionally produced and distributed videos, and copies provided to Hellyer of privately filmed footage are included. Among the latter are videos of film footage of Abu Dhabi from the 1960s that were transferred to VHS cassette in the 1990s, and the former include documentaries about wildlife, the desert, and other related topics, produced by oil companies (ADCO, Shell) or local agencies (ERWDA, Cultural Foundation). Also included are lectures given by Hellyer at local venues, such as the Emirates Natural History Group, or at an event organized by the United States Embassy in Abu Dhabi.
Excavations (Archaeology) -- United Arab Emirates; Excavations (Archaeology) -- United Arab Emirates -- Abū Ẓaby; Birds -- United Arab Emirates; Natural history -- United Arab Emirates; Journalists -- Abū Ẓaby (United Arab Emirates); Hellyer, Peter
- Abu Dhabi Islands Archaeological Survey (ADIAS), 1985-2006
  - ADIAS consultancies, July - September 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ADIAS consultancies, September 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ADIAS consultancies, May 1998 - January 1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1998: January - March (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1998: April - May (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 1998: June - September (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Correspondence to, 2002, March-November (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bowardi, Mohammed al-: Planning documents, miscellaneous, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Environmental documentary video: correspondence to Bowardi, April 1998 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Environmental documentary video: agenda and materials for meeting, 18 May 1998 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Environmental documentary video: copy of script, with edits by P. Hellyer), August 1998 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Finance records and memoranda [to be reviewed], 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Finance records and memoranda [to be reviewed], 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Finance records and memoranda [to be reviewed], 2001 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Maps: from ADCO and other sources, 1985-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - News clippings and newsletters, 1993-2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reports: Norman, Kirsty. "Conservation Assessment and Recommendations for Pearl House and Mosques on Dalma Island", May 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reports: "Report to ADCO on a preliminary survey of the Archaeology and Natural History of Jubayl Island, Abu Dhabi", January 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter. "A Preliminary Note on archaeological sites on the island of Qusabi, Abu Dhabi, UAE" [a report to ADCO], November 1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Report: Czastka, Wasse, and Strongman: "Preliminary Results of the November 1994 Archaeological Survey of the island of Lifiyya, Abu Dhabi, UAE", November 1995 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter and Aspinall, Simon: "A preliminary report to ADCO on an Archaeological Baseline Study of the Shanayel, Rumaitha and Dabbi'iya oilfields, North East Abu Dhabi", December 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Report: King, Geoffrey, et.al.: "A preliminary report to ADCO on a Survey of Jebel Dhanna: Archaeology, Environment, and Protection", December 1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Report: Carter, Robert. "A preliminary report on the ADIAS Ceramics Collection", February 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Report: King, Geoffrey, et.al.: "A final report to ADCO on an Archaeological Baseline Study of the ADCO oil fields; Part One: Coast and Islands", September 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter. "A Manual for the Recognition of Archaeological Sites and a Code of Practice for Reporting, submitted to ADCO", October 1999 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter and Beech, Mark: "Carbon 14 dating of Archaeological Sites on the island of Rufayq, Abu Dhabi" [a report to ADCO], January 2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Report: Hull, Daniel, and Hellyer, Peter: "Probable Fossil Animal Footprints at Mleisa, Western Region, Abu Dhabi", May 2001 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter: "A report on a preliminary archaeological survey of the Qidfa to Al Ain pipeline route", December 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Report: Hull, Daniel. "Archaeological Phosphate Analysis of Soil Samples from Jebel Dhanna, Abu Dhabi", March 2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Report: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter: "An Ecological and Archaeological / Palaeontological Review of the ADCO Main Oil Line, from Jebel Dhanna to Habshan", April 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter and Aspinall, Simon: "Ruwais Industrial Hazardous Waste Facility: Environmental Study (Archaeology, Palaeontology, and Ecology)", April 2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Report: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter. "Report to Abu Dhabi Gas Industries Ltd. (GASCO)...Palaeontological Survey of Future GASCO Ruwais train 3 site", September 2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Report: King, Geoffrey, et.al. "Archaeology at site of Proposed New Runways and Terminal at Abu Dhabi International Airport, a report to Parsons International", June 2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Report: Kallweit, Heiko. "An Archaeological Baseline Survey of Sadiyat Island, Abu Dhabi...(a report to Dome International)", June 2005 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Report: Beech, Mark and Hellyer, Peter: "Fossil Site at Umm al Ishtan, Western Region, Abu Dhabi", 25 November 2005 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Report: Stewart, John, et.al.: "A New Fossil Vertebrate Locality in Umm al-Ishtan, Western Region, Abu Dhabi--a preliminary report", February 2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Report: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter: "A survey of Archaeology and Palaeontology in the Shah oilfield, Abu Dhabi", February 2006 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Report: Hellyer, Peter. "A rapid pre-seismic assessment of Archaeology and Palaeontology in the Ruwais Oilfield, Abu Dhabi" (a report to URS-Dames and Moore), February 2006 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Report: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter. "An Archaeological Baseline Study of Areas A&C, Khalifa Port, Taweela, Abu Dhabi,", May 2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Reports: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter: "Environmental Assessment of the RW-08 rig/well location, Ruwais oilfield, ADCO", November 2006 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Archaeology and cultural heritage, 1979-2022
  - Conference program: "The Arabian Gulf in Late Antiquity and Early Islam," Al Ain, November 2022 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - News clippings: archaeological sites in the UAE, 1988-2009 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - News clippings: Conference on Archaeology, Abu Dhabi; and visit of Sir Donald Hawley, April 17-18, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs: excavation sites in the UAE (images by Peter Hellyer), 1995-1998 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reports, general: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter: Umm Shaif-Habshan pipeline (Khuff Gas Feed), EIA, report to Penspen International", November 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reports, general: American University of Sharjah: "Reconstructing Building Histories and Restoring the Past at Mleiha, Sharjah," HRM 494, Spring 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reports, general: Parsons International: "Early Works Environmental Assessment Report concerning the Rough Grading Project for the New Runway Area" [Abu Dhabi International Airport], Parsons International Limited, April 2005 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reports, general: Al Ain Cultural Heritage Management Strategy (UNESCO / Abu Dhabi Government), February 2005 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Reports, general: UNESCO; Abu Dhabi Tourism Authority. The Abu Dhabi Cultural Heritage Management Strategy. Final Report, November 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Reports, general: Hellyer, Peter and Aspinall, Simon. "An Archaeological Baseline Study of the south-west area....Reem Island, Abu Dhabi", June 2006 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reports, general: Hellyer, Peter. "A review of Archaeological and Palaeontological data Relating to the Main Oil and Gas Line routes from Asab to Habshan and Ruwais / Jebel Dhanna...", November 2006 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Reprints: Jackson, Peter; Coles, Anne. "A Windtower in Dubai," Art and Archaeology Research Papers, June 1975 (photocopied), with not from co-author, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Reprints: Abu Ezzah, Abdullah. "The political situation in Eastern Arabia at the advent of Islam," Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies, Vol. 9, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reprints: Arnold-Biucchi, Carmen. "Arabian Alexanders," from Mnemata: papers in memory of Nancy M. Waggoner (American Numismatic Society), 1991 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Reprints: Digby, Simon. "The Broach Coin Hoard as Evidence of..." Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, 1980, author inscription to Peter Hellyer in Jersey, September 1999 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Reprints: Potts, D.T. "Four Seasons of Excavation at Tell Abraq" (with inscription to Peter Hellyer), Proceedings of the Seminar for Arabian Studies, Vol. 23, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Reprints, unpublished: King, Geoffrey. "The paintings of the pre-Islamic Ka'ba," Paintingsfest, 19 June 2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Reprints: Hellyer, Peter. "The Archaeology of the Sabkhat of Abu Dhabi," in Sabkha Ecosystems, pages 325-333 (Kluwer), 2002 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Topical: Elazawy, Abd Alastar. "The Guidebook of Antique Buildings in Delma Island", undated, circa 1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Topical: UNESCO mission: to investigate inclusion of Sir Bani Yas island on list of World Heritage Sites (correspondence, reports, program of visiting delegation), March 1997 - January 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Topical: Green, Stephen. "A possible Stone Age flint site found near Fili, Sharjah", January 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Natural history and wildlife conservation, 1984-2020
  - Birds: Records of species observed, Peter Hellyer, 1990-1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Birds: Hirschfeld, Erik, et.al. "Abu Dhabi Shorebirds Project 1994", January 1995 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia: correspondence with Michael Jennings, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia: general (forms and map), 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia (Riyadh): issues of newsletter, "The Phoenix" (2 issues, 1 duplicate), 1987, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia (Riyadh): issues of newsletter, "The Phoenix" (7 issues, with 2 duplicates), 1990-1999 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia (Riyadh): issues of newsletter, "The Phoenix" (4 issues, with 1 duplicate), 2000-2013 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Birds: Atlas of the Breeding Birds of Arabia: observer reports (Peter Hellyer), 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Birds: Aspinall, Simon. "Birds in Sabkha Environments," in Sabkha Ecosystems, pages 311-314 (Kluwer), 2002 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Birds: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter: "The Birds of Qasr al Ajban, with proposals on management. A report to H.E. Sheikh Nahyan bin Mubarak al Nahyan", February 14, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Birds: Aspinall, Simon and Hellyer, Peter. "Qarnein-Island of Birds. A report to H.E. Sheikh Hamdan bin Zayed al Nahyan", September 1995 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Birds: Launay, Frederic and Loughland, Ronald. "Mission Report on Expedition to Central Asia and Kazakhstan (9th April to 13th of June 1994) for the National Avian Research Center Abu Dhabi" (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Birds: National Avian Research Centre (NARC): Internal Research Report, no. 36: "An introduction to the climate of the United Arab Emirates," by Benno Boer, December 1995 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Birds: News clippings, 1987-2007 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Emirates Natural History Group: greeting cards, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)